ER dismissed him and said, "Nothing's
wrong with him. He's fine. Just give him
some Zopran. Give him some sugar. He
will be fine." And completely dismissed.
Didn't read the notes from the doctor.
It was in that time that I realized I'm
not just a mom and a marketing
professional. I have a new job title.
I'm now also a caretaker and I am the
records keeper. I've been able to
utilize AI to help me communicate with
them by taking their notes, having AI
help me decipher them. I've trained up
the AI tool to know what our day is is
like, what our healthy days are like,
and what our unhealthy days are like.
When I used this AI tool for those labs,
for that hospital visit, I plugged it
in. The physician came in probably an
hour or two later, and I showed it to
her. It gave her a different way of
thinking. It gave her another option of
a treatment that we could do. Today's
guest works at the intersection of
healthcare innovation, emerging
technology, responsible transformation.
Amanda Roser has spent her career
helping organizations understand not
just what new technologies can do, but
how they can be implemented in ways that
create real value for patients,
clinicians, and health systems. Ma
brings deep experience across digital
health, artificial intelligence, and
strategic innovation. Her work focuses
on helping healthcare leaders navigate
the practical realities of adopting new
technologies while balancing trust,
safety, and operational impact. She's
been closely involved in conversations
around how organizations evaluate
emerging AI capabilities, how they
manage risk, and how they translate
technological possibility into
meaningful improvements in care
delivery. What makes Amanda's
perspective especially valuable is that
she approaches these questions from both
a strategic and an operational lens. She
understands that healthcare
transformation does not happen through
technology alone. It happens through
governance, thoughtful implementation,
and leadership that is willing to ask
difficult questions about how innovation
should be introduced in complex care
environments. In a moment where
artificial intelligence is moving faster
than many institutions are prepared for,
Amanda has been part of the effort to
ensure that healthcare does not simply
adopt new tools, but adopts them
responsibly. Amanda, welcome to the
signal room.
Thank you so much, Chris. Thank for um
welcoming you to the call.
Well, it's my pleasure and I've been
looking forward to our conversation.
We've had some some really good uh
insights. We've been both uh seeing
lately and and a lot of the topics that
are being discussed or are actually
encouraging for a variety of reasons.
But one of the reasons that we're
talking today is because you you've had
some experiences that are actually
identifying areas where we just need to
do be do much much better. And in
particular, when we're dealing with
concepts like informed consent, we we
kind of think about it in a checkbox
kind of way, but we don't necessarily
think about all the different
perspectives that we have to account
for. And this leads us to what your
personal experience has been. You you
have a child who's had some, you know,
very complicated uh care uh due to
having some rare conditions. So I want
to talk about that and I'm really
excited for the audience to to hear this
perspective particularly if you're out
there and you're doing development and
design. This is a conversation for you.
So Amanda when you your child first
entered the health care system what did
you expect the experience to look like?
Yeah. So, um, first off, thanks thank
you so much for such a wonderful intro
about my background, who I am, and also
my experience within the health care
system that I kind of just we got thrown
into it because just like anybody with
any medical disorder, you you're not
planning for it. It's not part of your
agenda of from in my case of being a
mom, I was my original thought was I
would be going to the doctors for the
the colds that hit the the household or
the tummy bugs that hit. But our world
was became a little bit different back
in 2021. Wow.
When we experienced healthcare in a way
I just never imagined. And so I
originally when I when we my son got his
diagnosis when he was diagnosed back in
2021 I had so much trust in the health
care system. I was naive in that process
of systems are in place for the people.
But I quickly came to learn that systems
are are in place to work within silos
and it's not built to work within more
of that complex complex medical space of
a person. And so in my son's case, we
have a multitude of physicians that we
have seen over the years and each
physician works within their special
within their specialty as they should.
That is what they practice. That is what
they they know through and through and
that's how they truly become that deep
expert within that area whether it's
endocrinology, neurology, the gastro
area as well. And so everybody has a
special specialty just like myself. I
have a specialty in marketing. I am not
a medical professional. And so I put my
trust in the health care system that
they can do this for my son. They can
make him healthy. They can balance him.
But in actuality, it does take more than
just the physicians. It takes the the
caretaker and in my case being the
parent to be able to jump in, roll up my
sleeves, and help manage where where I
can to make movement happen.
Well, you've already framed something
that I don't think most people think
about. You and it's really the role that
you're talking about. I think it's not
something that is it's certainly not
laid out as as as a a purposeful
exercise that you have to deal with in
terms of taking ownership like you just
kind of indicated that the the health
system is expecting you to do. I think
that we have really done a poor job
honestly of designing these various
systems for workflows that are that
reflect reality for both clinicians but
also for patients. And I think both have
been sadly not uh focused enough on when
it came to the initial original designs
that we were now living with. So at what
point did you realize that you were
becoming the coordinator of your son's
care? Meaning clearly you just stated
that this is something that you've been
focused on.
So it kind of became clear early on. We
discovered my there was something going
on with my son in 2021 and it was it
started with an ER visit. Something was
off and so um we brought him to the
hospital just like any parent would do
when something seems off and you go
through the beginning stages of them
trying to understand him as a person and
then they start going through the
questions of well what is going on? we
we can put the band-aid on and give him
the the D10 fluids that he needs because
his glucose is low, but what what's
really going on cuz a band-aid would
only last so long and it's it's in that
time that the the tests start to roll,
right? And over time um within 2021
remember that this was back towards the
co times and so things were running a
little bit differently if you weren't in
critical emergency needs uh within the
co area right and so um things were a
little bit slower lab tests were slower
back then to get results and so they
started to run genetic tests at that
time to understand him a little bit more
because they realized this isn't your
typical low glucose case, there's
something else going on. And they ran
genetic panels in that time frame and
months go by, we finally get results
back from the endocrinologist who called
us at 6:45 at night. I will never forget
that that time frame and never have
received a phone call from a doctor at
that time, but she took the time because
it was real
and she explained to us what the test
said. From there, we were connected with
a geneticist, and this is all up in in
Boston. We're connected with a
geneticist up there. That was our second
doctor. We had an in endocrinologist,
then a geneticist, and then we were
introduced to a nutritionist, and then
we were introduced to a metabolic
specialist. And so the list began to
grow at that point. And in that, it was
in that time that I realized I need I'm
not just a mom and a marketing
professional. I have a new job title.
I'm now also a caretaker and I am the um
the records keeper. I am the man. I'm
the person who is managing. I'm my son's
nurse. I am the person who has to
provide the symptoms of the day-to-day
to the physicians to multitude
physicians.
And I'm the person that has to keep all
of these systems in order and place to
to where the physicians can all properly
care for my son. And I have to be that
person who's pushing as well to get the
physicians to speak to each each other.
And that's it was in that time when I
learned that when I be had to start
pushing for people to speak to each
other that I realized there is there's a
gap in the system. While these people
are incredibly smart, there's a gap
within the system of communication.
Well, and it's evident from just what
you shared in these last few seconds.
You had to become a translator. I mean,
it's not normal for people to talk about
having to have genetic panels, for
example. It's a lost stone. I mean, a
lot of what you're talking about is a
language that you had to learn in order
to be able to take care of your son and
advocate for him. It It's mindblowing.
First of all, that's extraordinary. And
I'm really glad that your family has you
there. And you, your son in particular,
has got a mom who's figuring it out.
We're ready to roll up your sleeves and
dig in and figure out what you have to.
That that's remarkable. At the same
time, I hope that we'll really learn
from your experience and be this
conversation that we're having will be
helpful to a lot of people. Um, if
you're out there, you're doing designer
systems, I hope you really take a good
listen to to what is going to talk to us
about today. So, we'll step over and
assume, okay, yes, this is an official
thing that you've got to deal with as a
caregiver. What is this coordination
work actually look like week to week? I
don't I don't know that people think
about this coordination activity from
the perspective of a caregiver.
Yeah. So, there's a lot of behind the
scenes that happens as there's a lot of
behind the scenes that happens within
our all of our physicians offices and
their clinics. I recognize that through
and through, but the day-to-day it's a
whole another level because I like I
mentioned just a minute ago, we're
tracking so much information. Um, one,
we're tracking because we need to be
able to manage and respond in the moment
in the day-to-day. But two, I need to be
thorough, especially in those early days
in the discovery stage of what's going
on. I need to be very thorough with our
tracking to allow for the physicians to
have a better understanding of what's
going on. That's an area another I feel
like over time I've been catching lots
of gaps um within the systems but being
able to provide what's happening day
dayto-day from my son's glucose dropping
because let's say he was incredibly
active on the playground physician is
not going to see that. or let's say his
ketones are going up because he's got a
stomach bug and um what's going on with
him with uh the genetic test that came
through of glycogen storage disease
which we can get into in a little bit
but it uh creates high ketones and low
glucose and so I have to monitor whe is
it food that's causing it is it activity
at home is it a bug that's hit him has
does he have a cold or flu I'm tracking
all those details to where over time we
can have a full understanding of how his
metabolic system works because every
person's metabolic system works
differently. I have a twin brother and
just because I have a twin doesn't mean
our body works the exact same way,
right? And just like my son just he has
this genetic disorder and there's
somebody else that has a genetic
disorder with that same same diagnosis
but their bodies will never work the
same. They it will act differently in
different activities and different
scenarios of life. And so I have to be
that recordkeeper of that information
and provide that to the physicians. Now
this is where the gap is in that
providing of information. Everybody
tracks information differently and
that's how data and information can get
missed and diagnosises can become slower
because while I'm tracking what I feel
is right needed to track, I'm tracking
it in a spreadsheet and it's great. It
works for me. the the doctor's able to
get the insights, but it's not going to
help the doctor understand um through
and through because there's not enough
specific data in that kind of tracking.
So, if there is a tracking system for
any child or adult that has a um whether
it's a gen a genetic disorder or
something that has just happened over
time, there needs to be a better system
in place for me to be able to easily
provide you that information. Just like
doctors order labs a specific list and
way they're getting that insight. There
should be something for the for the
patient as well to be able to properly
provide the insights beyond your typical
what is their temperature you know
insights
right
or uh detailed th thorough tracking
system. There's so many apps these days
that can be implemented there. We use
Epic within the Children's Hospital
system, which is a great system, but um
I feel like it's an underutilized system
from a patient's p point of view. Th
this is it's becoming clearer to me as
as you're you're talking, we're talking
about a really significant gap and
you're the one that's discovering where
these gaps are. This is something we
have to do better. There's no there's no
question about it. We we just we have to
do this. Now, you you've talked about a
lot of stuff that goes on outside of the
medical record, your own documentation,
and figuring out what it is that you
actually have to track. What are some
things that might surprise healthcare
leaders about how much operational work
families are doing?
What might surprise them is probably
one, the amount of tracking that I just
kind that I went through uh with the
spreadsheets, but every family is doing
something different in order to be able
to manage their day-to-day, and that
that makes sense. I think of my own team
within my marketing department. I have
some some teammates who are going to be
using, you know, old school notebooks to
keep things in order. I have other ones
that are using spreadsheets and then
then I have other ones that are using
project management systems. While I can
I always just really push people to work
within the similar system to where
information be can be easily shared,
they're still going to revert to what is
natural to them. And so with patients, I
think that's what's happening where
people are reverting to what is natural
to them, whether it's a spreadsheet, a
notebook, whether maybe it's an app um
that's helping them keep up with
information. But there's different ways
that patients are tracking information.
And I don't think physicians realize
those different ways to where if they
did realize, they would be able to help
guide to where information can better
get to the physician to make better
faster decisions. not be not necessarily
better decisions cuz their decisions are
great but faster decisions because
anything with health with uh health time
is of the essence and can't wait you
know weeks and months and years to get
answers because I'm tracking differently
than you work from a dayto day to being
able to make your discoveries
creating more efficiencies with
processes for patients will help support
not just the patient but the physician
as well I
I don't think that we can o overstate
the significance of what you're talking
about here. You actually done done some
some writing recently talking about how
rare disease caregivers have to learn
often. It's almost like learning a brand
new language in order to advocate
effectively. I think there's there's no
doubt I remember, you know, learning
very very early on in my my own career
basic medical terminology, but I was
working in in a in a health system. As
as a parent, it's not obvious that you
have to, you know, go ahead and start
learning how to translate the things
that you now understand better than
most. Talk about what that learning
curve looks like. I know it it cannot be
a comfortable place as you're just
starting out. What what does that look
like?
Yeah. No, that's a really great
question. And I feel like it's not a
question that is ever really addressed
with people that do work in the
healthcare system. I recognize the
reason of that. I think of myself. I'm
in marketing and I can speak the
marketing world language through and
through. But if I go talk to a nurse,
it's not all going to click and make
sense of what I'm saying. So I recognize
that there is going to be a learning
curve. But I think especially at the
beginning in in my son's case with the
uh genetic disorder that came in, there
wasn't much information on it. There was
one clinical publication or clinical
journal that was out there. I felt like
I was going back to high school biology
class and relearning things that just
were even foreign to me back in high
school. There were words and acronyms
and diagrams that were just way beyond
my knowledge said or my interest at the
time but couldn't let that be the reason
I to absorb the information because this
was and is our reality at the end of the
day. And so um the learning
it's not it's not just a grade you're
going for here. This is but my stakes
are much higher.
Yeah. I'm not trying to impress any
teacher here. I am trying to help my
son. I my ultimate goal in life as his
mother is for him to grow and thrive and
live a healthy, happy life. So, he's six
years old now. I wanted to be running
around with his friends and not have to
worry about major medical things or
worry about going to the hospital again.
So, back then, gosh, 5 years ago, it's
just wild to think it's been that that
long. It feels it does feel like
yesterday. It feels like a lifetime ago.
But I had to pick up that medical
clinical journal and I I read it whether
I knew it knew what I said or not. And
over time I did a lot of googling. What
does this mean word mean? What is this
term? Tell me what this acronym means.
What does this mean for a 2-year-old
boy? Lots of googling, lots of just
trying to find more papers to help me.
And the learning curve was real. But to
overcome that learning curve, I'm a
writer. I've always been. I've been
writing since I was a kid. And what I
would do is I wrote blogs in the
beginning to help me process what I'm
reading to help me decipher. And over
time it it evolved um from a from a blog
to writing a caretaker guide to being
very vocal on LinkedIn and sharing u
more about my LinkedIn, Instagram,
Facebook, but sharing about our journey
has helped me understand the language.
How does this kind of affect people in
in a situation where maybe a family
hasn't figured out the medical
terminology and not even sure you know
what to do about it? How does that
impact the communication in in your
experience between you know you as a
caregiver and the clinicians? I mean are
there moments that that communication
was problematic? I mean how does it
impact and do you feel like sometimes
there's a miss and it's not you know
what you're saying isn't being heard? So
I think just again thinking more in the
rare disease space, what we deal with
day-to-day, it's it's in the rare
disease area, glycogen storage disease
type zero. And so back then, what would
have been very helpful to help with that
learning curve for myself or any future
patients of a rare disease is for the
physicians to encourage the parents to
get involved and jump by. There's
Facebook groups out there and physicians
are learning more and more that these
Facebook groups are very powerful groups
and especially the rare disease
community, the Facebook groups, they're
pretty small and so it's easy to make
connections and have people that have
gone before you who have been walking
this road for 5, 10, 20 years um to help
you understand this world and understand
that while in the moment, in the thick
of it all, it feels incredible scary.
You You feel scary. You feel like you're
the only one. You feel like you're the
only one that needs to go back to high
school biology to learn these terms, but
the reality is you're not the only one.
There's so many people out there.
Tapping into the Facebook communities, I
think, is a valuable tool that can
support parents. And then from there,
there's organizations out there that I
didn't realize in the beginning. It took
me a few years to find these
organizations, but there are
organizations out there that um are
helping with patients. So for us,
there's the ketoic hypoglycemia
international group and that that
organization has been a wealth of
knowledge for me and especially in the
early days. They they've been able to
connect me with the right people to
understand what this all means and then
to understand that this isn't as scary.
It it's scary. I'm not going to diminish
that. But it's not as overwhelming as it
feels when you're in the thick of it.
This kind of stuff, it's it flies under
the radar so much when we talk about
things like interoperability. I know
it's a type of conversation anytime I
have a conversation with a physician,
but I think we're talking about an
aspect of that that's just not accounted
for. So, one of the challenges I hear,
and I think you mentioned this spec
specifically to me, is that there's
often times you going into an
appointment and it's groundhog day.
you've got to explain everything from
the beginning. What's the whole story?
Just start the conversation in in with
with a new person that's involved in the
care team.
Why do you think that happens so
frequently?
So, um it's funny you say that because I
was actually talking to a family member.
She has a twins that that have a um a
rare disorder as well. And we were both
venting to each other about having to
retell the story. And that's that's a
pretty common exhausting feel of many
caretakers of retelling the story
because you have to retell the story
from the beginning. We've had physicians
who will My son is 6 years old. I'll
have a physician ask me a question of
when did he take his first step? When
did what was his first food? It's been
six years and it's been a I feel like
I've lived 60 years with the amount of
medical things that we've lived through.
And so
I have to retell those stories from
sometimes those very minute details all
the way to the hospital visit to or to
the ER visits. And we've had a multitude
of ER visits. We go through he I will
get asked about labs that he had done 5
years ago or four years ago or last
year. I have to remember and recall all
of this. And um from a parent point of
view, a caretaker of an adult person as
well, anybody is exhausting and you're
going to miss information. I am not
perfect. I am not a robot.
Um I do not have photographic memory. It
will take me I will miss information.
It's it's the reality of um retelling
stories over and over. And um while it's
not intentional that I'm missing a piece
to the story, it's very it's another gap
within the system of of there not being
a place to have let's call it an
executive summary of somebody's health.
There's no place for an executive
summary for you the my new physician to
jump on the portal and just see that
synopsis of my son over the last 5
years. And I'm sure you you're the same
way, Chris. Executive summaries can be
adjusted over time. There should be a
place within every portal, especially
for somebody of any medical complexity
or rare disease. There should be a place
where there is that summary. We don't
need to necessarily house a 20page or a
20page document or a novel of somebody's
story. There should be some kind of
placement of an executive summary that
provides that synopsis of what's been
going on over the last 5 years to where
somebody can quickly click that, read
it, get a a highlevel understanding, and
then deep dive with whatever that moment
scenario is needed to deep dive into. So
what are some of the types of things
that that you know kind of get lost you
know in in between specialists even when
you're having to see so many people
clinicians to o over times it just seems
like there's got to be some things that
are lacking in terms of what is captured
in those conversations that in order for
it to be retained. I don't know if it's
a structural issue, workflow issue, but
I mean, what's your sense of what that
what that problem really is. What I'm
thinking is, you know, there's there's
clearly something that's missing because
you're having to repeat the same things
over and over again. What are what are
some of the things that are coming up
where you actually have to go through
and rehash it because there's no clearly
there's no indication that's been passed
from one physician to another, the
specifics that you recited the very last
time you were there. So, I don't know if
it's maybe they just don't have a place
to capture it or is it just simply that
there's just so much that you just
possibly can't you can't possibly
remember everything.
Yeah, I think it's a bit of both in all
honesty. Um there is I to my knowledge I
haven't seen anything within a system
and I'm just going to use Epic because
everybody knows the Epic system and it's
in a lot of hospital systems as well.
But there's a lot of areas within that
portal and there's a lot of information
that it starts to gather over time. And
so I think what's missing is that there
needs to be a way for them to easily
aggregate some of the information that's
being provided to create going to keep
it simple in business terms because I
work in B2B all the time, but um there
needs to be summaries. There needs to be
just like I have to do a a one-page
summary on any project that I do for a
client, there should be something like
that for for the patients to where
information isn't missed. I think
information can be missed from whether
it's one physician orders a lab from
from let's say Quest Diagnostic and the
other physician order does labs
internally within their their clinic.
And so sometimes information doesn't
fully get across. there's other areas
that you have to click into or maybe the
physician received it via a email
document or a fax and the information
just doesn't get fully into the system
and so I think it's more it's a bit of
both of what your question was of
information is getting missed by
handover by different systems being used
and just everybody documents a little
bit differently
this is a I don't even know how to
describe it I just I can't help but feel
like this is just
an additional strain on a family who's
obviously already dealing with some
things that are incredibly difficult.
So, I mean I mean I don't mean to make
you think about this stuff any more than
necessary, but I mean talk about what's
that what's the impact of having to deal
with that repetition. I mean, where
you're already dealing with things under
stress. You're you're a mom, now you got
to wear this other hat. I mean, how does
this really impact you as a caregiver?
Yeah. So, there's actually a lot of um
there's more studies and information
that's coming out from a care
caretaker's point of view and there is
an um there's an emotional toll that
comes into play when you are a
caretaker, but then there's that
heaviness and that kind of burden feel
where you're having to manage every
little entity. And I wouldn't change it
for the world be what I'm doing from the
dayto-day because I see my son thriving
and that means the absolute world. We
have gone we went um my before my son
got a G ttube gastro button. He we my
husband and I were constantly waking up
every 3 to four hours checking his
glucose. His Dexcom was going off in the
night checking why why is that
happening? Giving him his nighttime
medicine to help with his glucose. So
the exhaustion that naturally happens
with certain complexities of medicine
it's real. So take that layer right
there and then add the layer of the
exhaustion of calling the insurance
companies to make sure things are being
covered and a doctor is in network to
doing the research about a new medicine
that they that the doctor wants to start
or maybe a new test, a fasting study or
a lab, new labs that need to be run.
Doing the research to understand what
the doctor is talking about. the
heaviness of being able to juggle all of
the there's a time schedule that my son
has to be on and the exhaustion of
keeping up with that making sure doses
aren't missed. It's a lot to juggle from
a caretaker point of view and the the
heaviness and emotional weight it can
take a toll on a caretaker taker over
time.
Yeah. you know, you're listening to
this, you know, it's clear that families
are having to take on a a role. It and
it's been not necessarily recognized and
sanctioned as part of a care team, but
it really really is. We have to think
about it differently, for sure. I mean,
you're talking about having to keep
track of so many things in between
appointments. I mean, what happens when
coordination breaks down? I mean, that's
that's the reality even under normal
circumstances. there's challenges with
that with a care team that's working
inside of a a health system and this is
a whole different level that that you're
talking about. I mean, what are some of
the things that that you've seen really
kind of go sideways because this is not
really a process that's understood or
well coordinated from both sides? I
mean, you shouldn't know have you
shouldn't have to know how to do do all
of this stuff, right?
And there's so much of it that maybe
isn't even understood by the care team.
Yeah, really great question. So, I
actually have two great scenarios of
instances where I saw a major breakdown
where it took, you know, myself, I had
to really roll up my sleeves to to
ensure that my son wasn't affected by
that breakdown. And so, what earlier
instance with my son's genetic disorder,
it is on the rare side. It's a little
the way of his genetic disorder is a
little bit complex and different than
the average. And so there we had a
hospital visit and um we we were out of
town on vacation. We were not near our
typical hospital and um brought him to
the ER and the E er dismissed him and
said it's nothing's wrong with him. He's
fine. Just give him some give him some
Zopran. Give him some sugar. He will be
fine. And completely dismissed. didn't
read the notes from the doctor from our
other location, our our main hospital
system, our main physicians. Doctor did
not read that information. He just he
knows what low glucose means. He treated
him for that. He treated him for a
stomach bug and he sent us on our merry
way. And what ended up happening is the
I think it was later that it was later
that day it turned into a even bigger
emergency where um I we couldn't keep my
son awake and so we had to we brought
him to a different hospital who took the
time to read his chart who actually
reached out to our doctors up in Boston
when we lived up in Boston. Um the
doctors and um residents, it was a
mixture of of people. They took the time
to read about my child, even though they
never have cared for someone like my
son. They took the time and they didn't
just go off of, you know, typical
clinical in the- moment ER, let's put a
band-aid on it. They took the time to
understand what truly is happening. They
did not dismiss my son and he got the
proper care he needed to balance him to
where once we did leave the hospital. I
think it was three days later. My son
was run running in the sprinklers with
his with the other kids. He was totally
fine. But if it wasn't for that, it
could have been a different story.
Sure.
And um I think that's one break in the
system is is knowledge and understanding
that we need to think one step further
than just putting that band-aid on that
patient that comes through those ER
doors. So that's one one scenario for
you. The other scenario is more on the
administrative side where there's a
breakdown in understanding for myself to
know what the process is for I was
trying to move my son from one hospital
to another hospital and um because we
had a a few doctors within one hospital
system and I was trying to bring
everybody together because working with
two different systems that's exhausting
and making sure information is getting
across and so I thought I was doing the
right thing moving them from one
hospital to the other hospital for
regular clinical physician care. Well,
the way I was going about it wasn't the
right way. And so, it took us 3 weeks to
actually get movement to get my son to
be transferred because while I was
calling it a what was the word I was
calling it? I was calling it a transfer
of care, they were calling it a referral
or no, they were calling it a second
opinion. They were calling they were
saying that I was looking for a second
opinion. And when you're looking for a
second opinion, it's a different process
of levels of priority of when you get
that next appointment.
Yes.
And so because we were speaking two
different formats of words to be able to
get my son with that other that clinic
within that hospital with the with our
endocrinologist, it took a longer amount
of time. And it did take me to become
vocal on LinkedIn for people to hear me
and see me. And that's a break a break
in the system because I do marketing
every day. I don't know the
administrative system. I don't know the
processes. And then once we were in the
doctor told me what what I should have
done to get him moved. It was I should
have just reached out to our
endocrinologist and the endocrinologist
at that clinic could have done the move
for us versus me doing this other this
other way that seemed like the right way
but it wasn't the right way. So there's
a break in the understanding for the
patient to understand processes of
administration systems.
Yes. And clearly there's a there's a gap
in our understanding of really how to
coordinate things effectively. We think
about interoperability a bit like a
checkbox and sadly uh most provider
clinicians understand that it it's
really an obstacle. They're very
frustrated by it. At the same time on
the other side of it you're very
frustrated by it. So the the clinician
and the patient are not being well
served by these disperate systems and
the fact that we're not doing the
integrations to to make sure that you
have the information that you need when
you need it. This is a gap I've not
heard explained the way that you're
you're explaining it. I think it it
needs to be heard. We do have to do
better. So I guess interesting enough
one of the ways that you and I connected
to begin with was talking about you know
what what's the role that AI has can
play. Um you've mentioned it's helped
you more than you expected. Maybe talk a
little bit about how you're actually
using tools like that to prepare for
your appointments or to communicate with
your your physicians. Um, so AI has
really I I feel like it's really
evolving the way that parents and
caretakers are able to commun
communicate with physicians and
clinicians because I'm not an expert. I
am not I do not have an MD and I I have
no science background. And so speaking
their language has been difficult over
the years and has been timeconuming. And
there's so many late nights that I spend
till 1:00 a.m. trying to get the right
way to speak to the doctor to have them
think a little differently or think
outside the box um when it comes to
care. And so I've been able to utilize
AI to help me communicate with them by
taking their notes and helping having AI
help me decipher them, taking labs,
helping that helping um having AI help
me decipher through that as well. And
one of the unique things that I have
within my within my AI tool that I'm
using, I also have within there our
day-to-day. I have what symptoms that we
see that the doctors don't see. I have
information in there about what the
day-to-day looks like for my son, what
the what uh the labs look like from what
we just had yesterday. But I also have
in there what the labs looked like four
years ago. I'm asking it for I'm help
having it ask provide information that
helps me understand what the doctors are
doing, but I'm al also h having it help
uh the doctors understand where I'm
coming from and how I want to get the
right care and movement for my son to
where he's not put into a box like the
kid next to him. He's his own box and uh
we need to open that box to be able to
think a little differently for the
day-to-day care.
It just seems like there's layer after
layer of additional things that are just
uh being put on your shoulders as as a
caregiver. This is mind-blowing to me.
Um are there things that that you're
using the capabilities for that you
think would be surprising to clinicians
at this point?
So um I my son was actually in the
hospital back in August. So, it was
about a 5-day hospital stay and the
doctors were really trying to figure out
what was going on and because it was it
was different from the typical reason we
were there. And so, what I ended up
doing was it was taking forever to see a
physician because they were packed that
day. I think there was some kind of cold
or bug that was hitting the hospital
pretty hard that and um I was getting
the labs. The labs were coming to me
through the through the portal. So, I
saw everything that was coming through
and what I was doing was I was taking
those labs, I was putting it into the AI
that I've already trained up over the
years or over the last probably two
years, two or three years, two years.
Um, I've trained up the AI tool to know
what our what our day is is like, what
our healthy days are like and what our
unhealthy days are like. And so, when I
say unhealthy, sick sick days. And so I
was able to take those labs and plug it
into my AI tool to have it help me one
understand what's going on. Two, I would
ask it think outside of the box on other
things that could be going on. I would
ask it for things like what are some
western medicine approaches to helping?
What are some holistic ways of
approaching it? this I was I truly take
it to go incredibly beyond the box
because um we can sit here and think
like we do every for you know the other
person but my everybody is different. I
can't stress that enough. Every human is
different and I'm so grateful for one of
our physicians who's who thinks just
like like we do. He's actually our
endocrinologist. Uh Dr. Paul Thornton.
He has been a gift to us when it comes
to day-to-day care, but he thinks
outside of the box with us. And so when
I used this AI tool for those labs, for
that hospital visit, I plugged it in.
The physician came in probably an hour
or two later and I showed it to her.
Well, I first heard what she was what
her thoughts were. After that, um, I
said, "Can you take a look at what this
AI just told me?" She read through the
entire thing. She was impressed. She was
incredibly impressed. Now, a lot of what
it was saying was very similar to her
diagnosis as well. Um, but there were
some other additional supports that it
suggested to think about and to try if
cuz AI always says I'm not a healthcare,
I'm not a doctor, I I can't tell you to
do this. So, I respect that and
appreciate that little note is there.
But, it gave her a different way of
thinking. It gave her another option of
a treatment that we could do. And um I
think her surprise
really opened my eyes, my personal eyes
to I don't think physicians know that
patients are using it in this way. And I
think the physicians that recognize that
patients are using it in this way and
don't dismiss it and use it as a
supportive tool in their diagnosis.
Gosh, we can move mountains with t in
time, you know, when we can cut cut time
in half and move mountains for people's
health by utilizing a tool that can move
at lightning speed to support the
doctors who have been studying us in
practicing medicine for years,
right? Yeah. It it's I I remember seeing
different scenarios years ago when I was
actually working inside of a hospital
and people
at that point in time I mean frequently
they they looked like they were carrying
their weight of the world on their
shoulders and they don't they didn't
have any of the things that you've been
talking about but now even with all of
this stuff there's just an additional
level of weight that you have to carry
because of these things that you have to
be aware of and I'm glad the technology
is catching up, but at the same time, I
don't want us to be continuing business
as usual and uh leaning on this stuff as
a crutch that I think there's some
things that need to be need to be
changed in terms of how we think about
this. So, talk about kind of how things
really ought to be designed around the
realities. So, if health care systems
truly recognize caregivers as part of a
care team, which you've talked a little
bit about, what would you change first?
That's a really great question and a
really great point as well because I
have while in the earlier days I did not
feel like I was that bright support
supportive team for that position in the
early days because I was naive in the
early days to healthcare in general.
And over time um especially being a mom
to a a child with a with a genetic
disorder and that has some complex
needs, I've become an expert in my
child. I I joke sometimes that I I have
a medical degree. It my medical degree
is in in my son. I have I'm a I have a
mom medical degree, right? And while I
can't talk to you about heart disease, I
can't talk to you about broken bones or
uh neurological problems, I can talk to
you through and through about one very
specific thing and that is my son's
health. I can talk through and through
about ketoic hypoglycemia and how his
liver works. And so over time I have
become an expert. And I think one of my
messages to clinicians and health care
professionals is that parents parents as
well as caretakers they have that
operational side because we see the
day-to-day. We go beyond the clinical
moment. We we see the day-to-day of
what's going on with that patient. And
so RC at the table should be seen and
valued just as much as the physician who
has years of practice in healthcare.
While I am never going to say my
knowledge is more than a physician
because goodness gracious their
knowledge set in medicine in you know
Latin even to understand all of these
very complex medical terms. They are the
true experts. But experts can only go so
far if they don't have a sidekick. and
parents and patient advocates can be
that sidekick in that specific patient's
medical journey.
Yeah, I think this is a this is an
important thing for for us to really be
focused on and make make sure our health
care system leaders and and physicians
are are really hearing about this
perspective. You know, you've been
inside the health care system and
navigating it in a way most people only
see from the outside. If leaders are
who's who are really responsible for
designing health care particularly
during this transformational period that
we're in if they truly listen to
caregivers what signal would they hear
that today is really missing in the
system?
Yes. So um families families patients
we're living in a system but we're we're
not just living in a system we're
operating within it every day. And that
really needs to be recognized because
when you when you have the operator be
able to provide you with insights and gu
guidance on what's going on, actual
change can happen. We're able to see
where the gaps are because we're not in
the day-to-day of your business. We're
in the day-to-day of where the end user
is. We are your end user, right? And so
we see where the breakdowns are
happening in a different way that you
would have seen working within the
hospital system, working within your
clinic. And so being open and receptive
to being able to get guidance and
insights from a different point of view,
it can make change within within your
system and it can help the next patient
that comes in with and has no clue about
health the health care system or has no
clue about a genetic disorder can only
change when we let people who recognize
those gaps to to make those changes.
Amazing. This conversation for me has
been very very eye opening and I I know
it maybe it seems like I'm a little bit
maybe not feeling great about the
situation because of the way it's
impacted uh your your family and I'm
sure it impacts other caregivers. At the
same time, I'm encouraged in in what I'm
hearing from you and uh I think it's an
important very important thing that that
you're you're getting out there and
you're talking about this. It's so
important that people hear from you and
what your experience is and you know
this advocation that you're talking
about every patient deserves to have
that and we are really good in building
technologies but there's a lot of things
that we forget about and what it really
comes down to is we're talking about
human beings at the end of the day. All
of this stuff is about the relationships
between people and you know that's you
know whether it's a family member or
it's you and your clinician or or
however you want to think about it.
Everything that we're doing needs to be
wrapped around wrapping around
everything to do with care and we've got
to do a much better job. And I I am
excited about what can be done and where
we can go from here. And I sincerely
appreciate, you know, you reaching out
to me and we've had some really good
conversations and I'm I'm hoping that we
can have some more. I'll be I'll be
looking for some opportunities where
maybe we can create a vehicle that
allows you to to really talk to some
people who are in the throws of
designing and planning because this
really needs to be something we think
about the care team does include family
members. It includes the you know the
the caregivers especially in scenarios
where people are not in a sit in a
position to be able to handle everything
all by themselves. Um I was talking to a
clinician earlier and just the whole
idea informed consent. Well, you're
talking about technologies. What about
in emergency services if when a
patient's not able to give consent?
How how do that's a gap we have to think
think about which which is not top of
mind in every specialty but it is in an
emergency situation. The
activities that have to be coordinated
between a caregiver, a mom like yourself
and the clinicians who are taking care
of your son. These are things that we we
just need to make sure that we're
thinking about that as we design and
we're not gonna get bit by it after the
fact. We have a probably a very narrow
window to to get some things right when
it comes to how we're implementing, you
know, these AI capabilities from a
foundational level, but we've been going
at a very very rapid pace.
Yeah.
And I know people have been worried
about it. You know, I think there's been
some voices that said we we should slow
down. Uh, unfortunately I don't know
that that's going to be the case, which
just means that people like you and I,
we we've got to tag team and and really
try to push these conversations forward
to make sure that the patient and the
providers are not the last ones we think
about when it comes to what we're
designing for. They've got to be first.
And again, amazing. And I respect so
much what you've done thus far. And and
I think you can count on me to to
continue to be supportive in any way I
possibly can. And I can't thank you
enough for taking the time to to spend
with me today and this conversation. And
I certainly look forward to more
conversations in the future. And not
just the talking, but the actual uh
delivery of some results. I think we we
can we can have an influence, but we got
to tag team and make sure that people
are listening.
Well, I appreciate so much of your time
and inviting me to your podcast. Um, I
think there's, you know, so much
opportunity for uh patient advocates to
have a seat at the table and it's a
patient advocates are very much a
underutilized tool within the health
care system and I'm starting to see a
lot more movement. And I saw the a
conference that incorporated
incorporated a patient advocacy panel
which I thought was such a unique thing
because physicians got to hear from a
different point of view, a different
perspective and I so I I truly believe
the more we open up the doors to that
group uh change can move because at the
patients are the enduser of the health
care system right and we want to make
sure that the health care system is
built for the end user.
Absolutely. That's the whole point,
right? Thank you so much. It's been
been, you know, awesome to have you on
the show and I I I can't wait to have
you back. So, I'm pretty sure there's
going to be advancements going on and
I'll be looking forward to hearing
updates on on how your son is doing as
well. He's fortunate to have a great mom
and a great family around him. We'll
pray for his uh continued recovery and
really we'll look forward just to to
hearing the good things as as the days
progress.
Thank you so much. I appreciate that and
I look forward to future conversations
as well. I think we have a lot more to
talk about.
Thank you so much. That's it for this
episode of the Signar Room. If today's
conversation sparked something in you,
an idea, a challenge, or a perspective
worth amplifying, I'd love to hear from
you. Message me on LinkedIn or visit
cigarroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human.